Guide to the Robert P. Joyce Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert P. Joyce papers
1962-1980
MS 1901
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The collection comprises the memoirs and related writings of Robert P. Joyce, documenting his personal life, as well as his career in the United States Foreign Service and the Office of Strategic Services. There is a minimal amount of correspondence with Max Hayward, authority on Russian literature, and Paul Nitze, expert on United States foreign policy.
Joyce, Robert Prather
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the American Heritage Center, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Prather Joyce was born on October 17, 1903, in Los Angeles. He received his B.A. degree from Yale in 1926, and then studied at the École Libre des Sciences Politiques in Paris. Joyce joined the United Services Foreign Service in June 1928, and later held posts in Shanghai, China, and La Paz, Bolivia. During his time with the Foreign Service, he also held the posts of Third Secretary at the United States Embassy in Panama; the Third Secretary and Consul in Belgrade, 1938; and Second Secretary and then Consul in Havana, 1940. In November 1943, he resigned from the Foreign Service and joined the Office of Strategic Services. He rejoined the Foreign Service in 1947 as Consul General in Trieste, Italy. The next year he joined the State Department's Policy Planning Staff. Joyce later served as counselor at the United States Embassy in Paris, 1952, and at the American Embassy in Rio de Janeiro, 1956; special assistant and then acting director, 1958, in the Bureau of Intelligence and Research; and Consul General in Genoa, Italy, 1959. He retired from public service in 1962. Joyce died in London on February 8, 1984.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises the memoirs and related writings of Robert P. Joyce, documenting his personal life, as well as his career in the United States Foreign Service and the Office of Strategic Services. There is a minimal amount of correspondence with Max Hayward, authority on Russian literature, and Paul Nitze, expert on United States foreign policy.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Havana (Cuba); Paris (France); Memoirs; Hayward, Max, 1924-1979; Joyce, Robert Prather; Nitze, Paul Henry, 1907-2004; United States. Department of State; United States. Foreign Service; United States. Office of Strategic Services
- Correspondence
  - Hayward, Max, 1962, 1972, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Nitze, Paul H., 1975, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Washington Post, 1970 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memoirs
  Scope and Contents
  Photocopy of typescript.
  - Chapters 1-6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapters 7-11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chapters 12-18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapters 19-25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapters 26-28 and appendices (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Writings
  Carbon copies of typescripts.
  - "Report on Eastern Europe", Circa 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Tales From the American Foreign Service", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Foreign Service As a Career-Some Pluses and Minuses", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "This Year At Marienbad and Points East", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Untitled, Circa 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Deals with overstaffing of government agencies; presidential election between Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan.